Guide to the Ronald R. Spadafora Papers 1911-2018 (bulk, 1970s-2010s) MS 3134
New-York Historical Society
- Education. Policies & Procedures. Reference., circa 1986-2006 (Offsite-box 9559)
  NYC Fire Law Handbook (3) for 2001 and 2002. Bureau of Fire Prevention Violation Reference Guide, 1986. Binder of Rules of the City of New York (RCNY) re: fire prevention and fire department, 1998. Binder: NYC Fire Prevention Code, 1997. Binder: Advanced ICS: ICS for Command and General Staff, Complex Incidents, I-400, Student Workbook and Instructor Guide Nov 2006, from National Wildlife Coordinating Group.
- Education. Policies & Procedures. Reference., circa 1980s-2005 (Offsite-box 9796)
  Seems to be a set of 4 binders used by Spadafora for filing notices for professional reference or maybe initially as his fire tech/promotion training in the 1980s; labels indicate a core purpose, but various documents inserted and annotated over time. Binder labeled "ABC" (All Borough Circulars): 1980s-circa 2005 (one document is a summary of safety command investigative report for a fatal fire at 2530 Atlantic Ave in Brooklyn, 1999). Binder labeled "Regulations" which includes ref material/prep tests on various regs, including administrative ones, like applying for meritorious awards; holds photocopies of some narratives & applications for such awards. Binder labeled "TB (Training Bulletin): Foam" includes ref material/tests on that and on other hazards, 1980s-90s. Binder labeled "Communications" includes tests, etc., for 1980s-90s, with FDNY manual (revoked 1987); inserted is FDNY booklet "Developing Continuity of Operations Within FDNY", 2004. A fifth binder is unrelated, with a few reference materials on general investment strategies.
- Education. Policies & Procedures. Reference., circa 1990-2000s (Offsite-box 9830)
  Binder of daily training/drills (1994ish-2002ish). Binder: Battalion Chief's Aide Course. Binder: Chauffeur (fire truck driver) training school reference manual: ladder, 1990. Training/reading etc material for "Change in the fire service: The role of the supervisor in a changing workforce" re sexual harassment, discrimation, etc. FIRE-CAP Program Directory (Fire Dept Children's Assistance Program). Binder of reference material on firefighting procedures (FFP), engine company operations.
- Education. Policies & Procedures. Reference., circa 1997-2012 (Offsite-box 9839)
  7 binders labeled with numbers: 5, 6, 9, 10, 12, 13, 41 Transparencies, notes, outlines, floppies, reference material re: fire tech courses, lieutenant and chiefs promotion courses, and firefighting seminars. 1997-2012 (41). 41 has Under River Rail firefighting (2008) and loft (2011) procedures. See scope note for list of all related binders 1-48 and the boxes they are in. Packet of FDNY Orders 1997-2009, with Fire Bell Club of New York newsletters 2002-2011, and some miscellaneous memos. (Includes digital formats)
- Education. Policies & Procedures. Reference., circa 1997-2013 (Offsite-box 9855)
  6 binders re: fire tech training, labeled numbers: 15, 16, 29, 30, 35, 38. (See scope note for list of all related binders 1-48 and the boxes they are in.) One folder labeled "department orders" with various/miscellaneous memos, procedures, etc. circa 2000-2002; Holds laminated FDNY vehicle ID plates. Packet of issues of La Sotto Voce, newsletter of Columbia Association of FDNY (circa 2001-10), and related CD of Columbus Day Parade (photos?). Packet of issues of "In Command" by the Fire Chiefs Association, circa 1997-2013, plus related docs. (Includes digital formats, artifacts)
- Education. Policies & Procedures. Reference. Personal., circa 2000s-2010s (Offsite-box 9779)
  High Rise Inspection Training Program binder (circa 2005). Binder of miscellaneous reference material (articles, procedures, etc. re "fire prevention"). AFID-Battalion Chief training course binder, 2002; (AFID=Apparatus Field Inspection Duty); see also box 9778). NYS "Basic Course for Peace Officers" binder. A couple small folders of Spadafora personal things (parody mock-ups, cards, etc.). Oversize building information card and related form.
- Education. Personal., circa 2010s (Offsite-box 9546)
  Spadafora files mostly for courses he taught at MCNY, especially MPA (Masters of Public Administration) 542: "Public Safety in the 21st Century" and MPA 541 "Terrorism and Disaster Recovery." Files are mostly admin (adjunct faculty handbook, APA writing guide, etc.). Some student matter. circa 2011 and later. Some John Jay material, including a CD of John Jay back-up 2009. Continues in box 9547. (Includes digital formats)
- Education. Personal., circa 2011-2013 (Offsite-box 9547)
  Continued from box 9546. Spadafora files for MCNY courses Public Safety and others. Reading material, admin, syllabus, etc. 2011-13
- Education. Personal., circa 1980s-1990s (Offsite-box 9552)
  Materials related to Spadafora's Fire Science course at John Jay from 1989-mid 1990s: syllabuses, general John Jay pamphlets and policies, Fire Science course outlines/syllabuses from mid-1980s (from instructors prior to Spadafora), draft paper on arson by a SUNY-Stony Brook engineering student.
- Education. Personal., circa 1980-2009 (Offsite-box 9847)
  Thick binder re fire tech lieutenant and other officer level training, 2007-09. Same for company officer course, 2004-05. Envelope of FFP (firefighting procedures) questions, 1980-86 (fire promotion course); these are probably earlier versions of the 1990s-2010s fire tech materials in numbered binders in the collection; also these 1980s documents probably relate to when Spadafora took the courses as the documents are marked up.
- Education. Personal., circa 2000s-2018 (Offsite-box 9861)
  All relates to Spadafora's firefighter exam prep book. Folders of drafts, editorial comments, and the like. Reference material here is mostly other forms of study guides from San Antonio, Tulsa, Los Angeles, Phoenix, New Jersey. One thick folder includes the FDNY Recruitment and Diversity Unit's Firefighter Test Preparation exams and answer keys. Generally looks to be circa 2006-07, though some 2018 documents appear.
- Education. Personal., circa 2000s (Offsite-box 9862)
  Mostly drafts of chapters and practice exams of Spadafora's book on firefighting exam. One folder on firefighting physical agility exam has FDNY-related reference material. Has floppy disks with docs. (Includes digital formats)
- Education. Personal. Reference., 1948, circa 1978-2014 (Offsite-box 7433)
  Fire tech binders labeled 43, 44 (with various FDNY firefighting procedures and material for Spadafora's (instructor) 2013 Officer's Prep Course (with 2 unlabeled floppies), and 47 (for Spadafora's 2014 officer prep course, with CD. (See scope note for list of all related binders 1-48 and the boxes they are in.) Binder: Fire Tech Battalion Chief Promotion Course materials, 2008. Binder labeled "Promotions" includes: department orders and supplements to orders re: promotions and transfers, many if not all tracing Spadafora's rise through the ranks; congratulatory cards and some photos are in binder as well as other personal things (paystubs, etc.); also includes some general ref material on promotions in FDNY and an annotated 1980s fire tech exam; ranges from circa 1990s-2002. Binder labeled "Captains Exams" for various years, 1977-97. Loose training/exam related print matter. Spadafora's Probationary Firefighter Reference Manual, 1978. FDNY annual report, 1980. A 1948 invoice for bedroom furniture sold to Arnold Lord. (Includes digital formats)
- Education. Reference. Personal., circa 1997-2013 (Offsite-box 9838)
  Green Associate certificate, 2011 (expires 2013, so the box also holds related material for later years certification). Print matter/audiovisual: several books, CDs, DVDs, some floppies re: green construction, climate change, biodiesels/fossil fuels, and related. 3 copies of a CD-ROM: Instructor Resources to go with "Sustainable Green Design & Firefighting: A Fire Chief's Perspective" by Spadafora." Some folders with documents re Spadafora's recertification as Green Associate and docs re revising his "green book" through another publisher. Some loose email printouts re prepping for his John Jay course. Textbooks, memos, etc re: Incident Management system (IMS)/Incident Management Team (IMT)/Emergency Management Assistance Compact (EMAC); these are generally FEMA publications but IMT docs are specific to NYC. "Emergency Response to Terrorism" Student Manual and self-study guide, from the National Fire Academy, with miscelleous related documents inserted by Spadafora; guides circa 1997, inserts into early 2000s. "Fire Command" textbook. (Includes digital formats)
- Education. Reference., circa 1961-2010 (Offsite-box 9752)
  Print matter: books and other published things: Binder of published articles on fire loss management from "Fire Engineering" magazine. Binder of training bulletin "Management T-1" re teaching OTJ instruction (1961 version) by Delahanty Institute. 2 copies of binder from NYS Academy of Fire Science: "Student Manual: Building Construction for Fire Suppression Forces" (1986). Binder of guidance on "Municipal Fire Administration" (PACT program). Modern Fire Technology, Inc (Fire Tech) training memo series re: management (1979-81). 3 textbooks on firefighting. 5 textbooks on incident management, fire law, sports safety, management/Lombardi Rules. Fireline/wildfire handbook, and other incident management pocket reference books (2004-10).
- Education. Reference., circa 2000s (Offsite-box 7436)
  Binder of print matter/reading/reference material for Spadafora's course FIS 101, Intro to Fire Science (uses textbook Introduction to Fire Protection, 2nd ed, by Robert Klinoff), with syllabus, Spring 2006. Print matter: 4 books: "The Sacred Fire," "Historic Fires of America," "Life Safety Code Handbook," and "Strategic & Tactical Considerations on the Fireground."
- Education. Reference., circa 1988-1990s (Offsite-box 9891)
  4 binders of reference/reading material related to Spadafora' Fire Science 101 course at John Jay, 1994, with later inserts. Binders are structured by chapter, presumably based on text: " Principles of Fire Protection" by Arthur Cote & Percy Bugbee, NFPA, 1988. Also, a packet of student midterm reports (1989) on historical fire disasters and related tearsheets.
- Education. Reference., circa 1980s-1990s (Offsite-box 7440)
  4 binders of print matter (tearsheets, brochures, etc.) re: Spadafora's Fire Science course, arranged loosely by chapter. Appears to have been started for the 1989 course he taught, but material dates out to the late 1990s. Packet of "exceptional student papers" from 1992-93.
- Education. Reference., circa 1999-2013 (Offsite-box 9557)
  Binder: Fire Service Joint Labor Management Wellness/Fitness Initiative: Candidate Physical Ability Test (has 2 videocassettes along with the paper material), 1999. Print matter: 5 math books and 2 shrinkwrapped packages of pamphlets on Explosion Protection Testing Services by vendor Fike (many copies, can be reduced). FDNY Firefighter candidate Physical Preparation Guide, 2013. 5 CDs on lightweight construction. (Includes digital formats, video)
- Education. Reference., circa 1997-2000s (Offsite-box 9560)
  Several files on specific local laws/codes/standards, with reference material and some memos related to the laws/codes, circa 1997-2004. Booklet: Fire Prevention Continuing Education (Fire Officers Management Institute, 2006). Binder with NFPA 10 (Standard for Portable Fire Extinguishers). Binder with NYC Fire Prevention Code, 1997. Binder of various local laws. NYC Building Code. CD with FDNY phone book and building laws. (Includes digital formats)
- Education. Reference., circa 2000s-2010s (Offsite-box 9749)
  Mostly training-related: Binder of training material: S-420 wildfire incident simulation (Fall Creek Fire). CD "Fireline Safety Refresher Training" and related papers. Documents re: Missoula firejumpers, likely related to the wildfire and fireline training. Some travel advisory docs re: South Africa. Binder from Homeland Security re: preparedness "Preparation for Initial Company Operations: PICO Instructor Guide". Also 6 print matter on medical/health (emergency transport, EMT prehospital care, life support, disease transmission, artifical respiration, and the like). (Includes digital formats)
- Education. Reference., circa 2009-2012 (Offsite-box 9772)
  Spadafora files for course taught in fire tech at John Jay, 2009-2012ish: student work, rosters, reading material, etc. Continues in box 9773.
- Education. Reference., circa 2009-2012 (Offsite-box 9773)
  Continued from box 9772. Spadafora files for course in fire tech at John Jay, 2009-2012ish: files of reading material, background, product info, notes for class, etc. All technical: carbon dioxide, halon, clean agents, environmental issues, and the like. CD and floppies, some from vendors. (Includes digital formats)
- Education. Reference., circa 2008-2013 (Offsite-box 9775)
  Spadafora Fire Safety Administration course and Fire Protection course (FIS/Fire Science courses) for circa 2008-13: various files of outlines, reading material. Related videocassettes. Related textbooks. (Includes video formats)
- Education. Reference., circa 1990s-2015 (Offsite-box 9788)
  1 copy of Spadafora's Firefighter exam, 2nd ed, 2015 book. 6 other textbooks on firefighting, some with additional inserts. Videocassette: NFES 2499 I-100: Module 1: Introduction to ICS, 1996. 4 CDs re: wildland fire behavior, unified command, incident management. A South Africa related book on leadership. A children's book on wildfires. (Includes digital formats, video)
- Education. Reference., circa 2000s-2010s (Offsite-box 9791)
  Several copies (various editions) of Spadafora's Firefighter Exam prep book (McGraw-Hill). Two copies have many inserts of student-related and other course stuff by Spadafora, with some reference/reading material (circa 2008). Copies of Spadafora's two books: "Sustainable Green Design & Firefighting" (2013) and "Fire Protection Equipment and Systems" (2015). Marketing brochures, CDs, portfolio, etc re: F-500 Encapsulator technology. (Includes digital formats)
- Education. Reference., circa 2000s-2010s (Offsite-box 9823)
  Print matter: Mostly firefighter exam prep books. Other prep books for armed services vocational aptitude and GRE. Other books on algebra. A FDNY DVD re candidate tutorial (2006) and a CD "Proby Manual." (Includes digital formats)
- Education. Reference., 1911, circa 2000s-2010s (Offsite-box 9824)
  Print matter: Firefighters Handbook. Spadafora's McGraw-Hill Firefighter Exams, 2nd edition, practice tests. FDNY test preparation manual and memory examination booklet (many copies of both). DVD: FDNY Dept of Diversity & Recruitment candidate tutorial session (2006). A math book. A 1911 plane geometry workbook. (Includes digital formats)
- Education. Reference., circa 1982-2012 (Offsite-box 9829)
  WNYF & Medal Day 2010-12. Binder: "Procedural Guide: Company Officer" circa 1988-90. Binder: "Chauffeur Training School (CTS): Engine Reference Manual" 2004. Binder: "First Line Supervisors Training Program" circa 1986 with later tearsheet etc inserts. Binder: "FDNY Lieutenant's Assessment Orientation" circa 1982. Binder: "Fire Tech updates" 1995-2009 (these are updates and update announcements, not the promotion training course ones under the same "Fire Tech" brand heading).
- Education. Reference. (Offsite-box 9842)
  2 books. Bulk of box: Audiovisual: 25 videocassettes (firefighting training, "John Jay college films"), DVDs on research paper writing, armed services vocational aptitude testing, History Channel & "Hellfighters" movie, video game "Firefighter", FDNY training DVDs (fire investigation, welcome to FDNY, recruitment, etc). Several floppies with forms, docs. (Includes digital formats, video)
- Education. Reference., circa 1990s-2000s (Offsite-box 9843)
  7 binders labeled with numbers: 2, 19, 20, 23, 24, 27, 28, re fire tech course for officer promotions and firefighting, with Spadafora's overhead transparencies, etc. (See scope note for list of all related binders 1-48 and the boxes they are in.) Print matter: FDNY telephone directory 1988, various copies of "The Trumpet" newsletter of the Uniformed Fire Officers Association, various copies of "Viewpoint from 9 Metro Tech" newsletter of FDNY (2000s), and "FireWorks" 1990s newsletter from FDNY.
- Education. Reference., circa 1990s-2000s (Offsite-box 9844)
  7 binders labeled with numbers: 1, 17, 18, 21, 22, 25, 26, re fire tech course for officer promotions. Many floppies in binder pockets. (See scope note for list of all related binders 1-48 and the boxes they are in.) Also a package of photocopies re: command & control communications (walkie-talkies, etc.), 2000s. (Includes digital formats)
- Education. Reference., circa 1999-2011 (Offsite-box 9863)
  Spadafora files for Fire Science (FIS 401) and Fire Safety Administration (FIS 210) courses he taught. Student work (exams) and rosters/grades. Hand-outs, syllabuses, reference material. Courses appear to date from about 2009-2011, but print matter dates back to circa 1999.
- Education. Reference., circa 1990s-2000s (Offsite-box 9864)
  For course taught by Spadafora: Folders (based on various chapters) of reading material, course outlines, student work re: FS 401 (Fire Science) and FS 210? (Fire Safety). 2000s.
- Education. Reference., circa 2000s (Offsite-box 13878)
  Overstuffed binder labeled Training Bulletins (TB) A-Man. Topics include apparatus, arson, confined space operations, emergencies, fires, foam, forcible entry, management. The bulletins make up a small portion; the rest are tearsheets, magazines, etc on the related topic. Also here is a pile of tearsheets on various firefighting and management topics.
- Education. Reference., circa 2000s-2010s (Offsite-box 13879)
  Overstuffed binder labeled "Training Bulletins" including self-contained breathing apparatus (SCBA), rope, purple K chemical, search, tools, with tearsheets, etc inserted. Box also holds: NIOSH booklet on chemical hazards, Tunnel First Responder Manual Field Guide 2016 for Carey and Queens Midtown Tunnels, clipboard with some department orders, 3 training CDs, a pile of tearsheets on various technical matters. (Includes digital formats)
- Education. Reference., circa 1990s-2000s (Offsite-box 13880)
  2 overstuffed binders re: Hazardous material (Hazmat) tearsheets mostly, with related training bulletins. Binder "Permit-Required Confined Space (PRCS) Program from AT&T, with tearsheets and fire/EMS tactics and procedures guidance inserted.
- Education. Reference. Personal., circa 2000s-2010s (Offsite-box 7437)
  Set of files on technical topics that relate to both Spadafora's firefighting exam book and his class on FIS 401, New Technology in the Fire Service (Fall 2011). Topics include: Plastics/ flame resistant technology, fire retardants, nuclear power plants, powdered aerosols (lots), fire dynamics simulation (lots), general firefighting history, disasters, on the job scenarios. Material includes papers (including student papers), tearsheets, print-outs, vendor product brochures (e.g. Stat-X fire suppression systems), CDs/DVDs (including a mailer from NIST with several disks re simulations, reports, etc.). Includes a packet of material from a Hospital Safety Conference at Mt. Sinai (2010) and approval of Spadafora's conflict of interest waiver request for writing the exam prep book. (Includes digital formats)
- Education. Reference. Personal., circa 2000s-2010s (Offsite-box 9202)
  Binder of Powerpoint slide presentation: "Structural Fire Fighter Assessment." Print matter: Emergency response texts, Spadafora's firefighter exam book, with lots of loose inserts and other print material in the box on various aspects of firefighting; some admin documents such as a contract. Many CDs and DVDs from FDNY for training. Some are unclear in content but appear to be related to particular incidents, possibly with digital photos. (Includes digital formats)
- Education. Reference. Personal., circa 1980s-1990s (Offsite-box 9794)
  Appears to follow from box 9793 to some extent. 2 binders of material related to Spadafora's course FIS 303 (Fire Science: Fire Investigations); Spadafora's appointment letter and course description in one of the binders; the 2 binders hold reading/reference material (circa 1993). One procedural binder re: arson, circa 1980s, with inserts into the 1990s. Booklet of reading material for FS 665, Legal Aspects of Fire Investgation (Part 2). Binder "Selected Articles for Fire & Arson Investigators, 1980 ed."
- Education. Reference. Personal., circa 1983-2000s (Offsite-box 9798)
  Binder of photocopies of papers/articles re: arson from a criminal justice, insurance, socioeconomic perspective (rather than science/investigation). A few loose print matter on arson/crime. Binder of print matter on NFPA 921 (NFPA=National Fire Protection Association), Fire & Explosion Investigations, and NFPA 907M (electrical Fire Causes), 1992, 1988. Binder: Fire Marshal course material, annotated, 1983. Binder of overhead sheets and print matter re: seminar in fire safety & investigations. 2 binders (books 1 & 2) for Spadafora's FIS 303 (Fire Investigations) course (the binder has the 1993 list/key of Fire Science courses at John Jay College of Criminal Justice: FIS 101 is Intro to Fire Science; FIS 205 is Fire Service Hydraulics; FIS 301 is Fire Dept Organization & Admin; FIS 303 is Fire Investigations). Also includes some Spadafora personal things: letter re foreign service test results, file on attempt to test for FBI special agent; photocopy of pistol license; annotated NYPD telephone directory.
- Education. Reference. Personal., circa 2000s-2010s (Offsite-box 9859)
  Spadafora's book "Firefighter Exams": Copies of the 2nd edition (2015). Copy of the 1st edition (2008) with materials inserted into it. Reference material and notes related to the book, including FDNY test prep manual, memory exam booklet, and a competing (Barron's) exam prep book. Contract amendment from McGraw Hill for book. Some files on technical matters not obviously related to book: binder re rangehood fire inspections; report of the FDNY mega-high rise committee (2017). A portfolio with personal material: medical matters, pension matters, and Rhonda Shearer/Spadafora's certificate of domestic partnership (2018).
- Education. Reference. Personal., circa 2000s (Offsite-box 9868)
  Thick folder of student work, grades, course proposal, syllabuses, etc. for courses taught by Spadafora. Various files on fire science matters (tearsheets, etc.): smoke control, fire suppression/water mist, robotics, seismic, specialty window systems info bulletin from FDNY (with CD), simulator training, SCBAs (self-contained breathing apparatus). (Includes digital formats)
- Education. Reference. Specifics (Boat/ship committee), circa 1990s-2010s (Offsite-box 9750)
  Clipboard with documents: NYC Boat/ship committee members, with procedures, ship descriptions, and related. Bulk of box holds photocopies of articles and other ref material that look to be in connection with Spadafora's courses on fire science (circa 2006), including course outlines. Booklet "Firefighter Information Tutorial" (2012).
- Education. Specifics (Big Cougar fire), circa 2010s (Offsite-box 9543)
  Spadafora course at MCNY: Intro to Homeland Security, 2015. Print matter: "Terrorism and Homeland Security" text by Philip Purpura with many inserts, including syllabus and tearsheets. Binder has the instructor's manual to go with text. Rest of box has other texts and print matter re terrorism. There is also an After Action Report for an ICS collaboration re Big Cougar Fire, 2014.
- Education. Specifics (Fire Department High School). Personal. Reference., circa 2000s (Offsite-box 9760)